Guide to the Samuel Miller Brownell Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Samuel Miller Brownell papers
1923-1986
1966-1975
MS 1491
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
5
The papers consist of correspondence, funding proposals, project reports, subject files, writings, research material, and printed materials that document the career of Samuel Miller Brownell as an educator and consultant in the field of urban educational administration during his tenure at Yale University and the University of Connecticut. Brownell's contributions to the creation and administration of the Mid-Career Program in City School Administration at the Center for the Study of Education at Yale University comprise the main focus of the collection.
Brownell, Samuel Miller, 1900-1990
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Samuel M. Brownell, 1989.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series: I. Yale Files, 1923-1982. II. Mid-Career Program in City School Administration Files, 1950-1986. III. University of Connecticut Files, 1966-1970.
Biographical / Historical
Samuel Miller Brownell was born in Peru, Nebraska, on April 3, 1900. He received a B.A. degree from the University of Nebraska in 1921, an M.A. from Yale in 1924, and a Ph.D. from Yale in 1926. Brownell was superintendent of schools in Grosse Pointe, Michigan, from 1927 to 1938. From 1938 to 1953, he was a professor of educational administration at Yale. He served as president of New Haven Teachers College from 1947 to 1953. Brownell served as the United States commissioner of education from 1953 to 1956 and was superintendent of schools in Detroit from 1956 to 1966. He returned to Yale University in 1966, accepting a joint position with the University of Connecticut as a professor, advisor, and consultant in the field of urban educational administration. Although his assignment at the University of Connecticut was completed in 1970, he continued his role at Yale University until 1973. Brownell died in 1990.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, funding proposals, project reports, subject files, writings, research material, and printed materials that document the career of Samuel Miller Brownell as an educator and consultant in the field of urban educational administration during his tenure at Yale University and the University of Connecticut. Brownell's contributions to the creation and administration of the Mid-Career Program in City School Administration at the Center for the Study of Education at Yale University comprise the main focus of the collection.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Education -- Study and teaching; Education -- United States; School administrators -- In-service training; School management and organization; Educators; Brownell, Samuel Miller, 1900-1990; Yale University. Center for the Study of Education. Mid-Career Program in City School Administration; Yale University. Dept. of Education
- Yale Files, 1923-1982, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  The Yale Files document the primary initiatives of the education department of Yale University with which Samuel Brownell was involved, mainly from the mid 1960s to the mid 1970s. The General files, arranged chronologically, deal primarily with the administration of the department during Brownell's early years at Yale and there is great overlap of subject matter among folders. Topics include staffing issues; registration procedures; statistics and projections; budget items; curriculum content; publicity; reports; proposals; and related items. The succeeding subject files focus on the various education courses available on the undergraduate and graduate level for advanced teaching degrees, as well as outreach programs within the community for high school students. These files are arranged alphabetically by topic or title and chronologically within a topic. The folders contain materials created and acquired by Samuel Brownell as a member of a committee or board. Not only is Brownell's contribution to the teaching administration program at Yale documented, but also a history of the department of education at Yale University during his tenure.
  - General, 1923, 1938-1972, undated (Box 1, Folder 1 - 14)
  - Center for Education Studies [program for advanced studies in education; includes first newsletter], 1968, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Child Study Center, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Committee on Elementary and Secondary Education, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 17 - 18)
  - Council Committee on Graduate School, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Department of Psychology [Yale Conference on Learning], 1966 December (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - General Education Seminar
    - Education 200, 1937-1954 (Box 2, Folder 21 - 33)
    - Education 215a/b, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Education 305, 1945-1946 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Graduate School Executive Committee, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Institute of Social Science (ISS)
    - Interim Advisory Board, 1969-1970 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    - National Science Foundation grant, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Institution for Social and Policy Studies (ISPS)
    - General, 1973-1980 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Spencer Foundation proposal, 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Inter-Visitation Committee, 1952 December (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Law School seminar [Legal Problems of the City and State: Public Schools], 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Lee, Richard C. ["Urban Renewal: Myth or Reality"], 1971 February (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Master of Arts in Teaching program (MAT)
    - General, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Directors conference [includes annual report of MAT program, 1965-1966], 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Reform of program, 1968-1969 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Seminar [MAT 190], 1967-1970 (Box 3, Folder 47 - 51)
  - Post-doctoral seminar
    - 1966-1974 (Box 3, Folder 52 - 54)
    - 1973-1982 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - 1973-1982 (Box 4, Folder 56 - 58)
  - Teacher Preparation Program [includes materials relating to the study committee and undergraduate five year re-accreditation], 1954, 1970-1982 (Box 4, Folder 59 - 65)
  - Vassar-Yale Study Group, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 66)
  - Yale Summer High School
    - Background materials on urban studies and programs, 1967-1969 (Box 4, Folder 67 - 68)
    - Comments on consultant Arthur Singer's report, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 69)
    - New Haven schools, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 70)
    - Proposal, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 71)
    - Reports on sessions
      - 1967 (Box 4, Folder 72)
      - 1968-1969 (Box 5, Folder 73 - 77)
  - Yale Upward Bound Program, 1968-1977 (Box 5, Folder 78 - 87)
- Mid-Career Program in City School Administration Files (MCP), 1950-1986, Series II
  The Mid-Career Program Files document the contribution of Samuel Brownell in the creation and administration of the Mid-Career Program in City School Administration, the first operation of Yale's Center for Education Studies. Established in 1970, the non-degree program offered fellowships to approximately ten city school administrators, particularly minority members, annually for an academic year or a semester in residence. The program aimed to further the education and experience of city school superintendents, assistant superintendents, and directors of state and federal educational departments. Supported by the W. K. Kellogg Foundation and Yale University, the program was intended as a permanent one but was terminated in 1974 due to a lack of additional funding sources. The files consist of correspondence by and about the Fellows and resource persons involved in the program and are arranged alphabetically by personal or organizational name. The subject files contain drafts of funding proposals and trace fundraising venues. The series concludes with documentation of the Mid-Career Program arranged chronologically by academic semester, and alphabetically by subject within a semester. Materials referencing MCP are also interspersed in the subject files of Series I.
  - Correspondence
    - General (A-Z), 1970-1981 (Box 6, Folder 1 - 3)
    - Allen, Dwight, 1971-1972 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - American Academy of School Administrators/National Academy for School Executives (AASA/NASE), 1971, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Barnes, Melvin, 1970-1971 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Berry, Charles, 1973-1974 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Brackett, Pearl C., 1973-1974, undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Bush Leadership Fellows Program, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Calabro, John, 1972-1975, undated (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Campbell, Clyde, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Carpenter, Charles, 1974-1979, 1982, 1986, undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
    - Connor, John J., 1972-1975, 1980-1981, undated (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - Cranford, Evies, 1973-1974 (Box 6, Folder 14)
    - Curtis, William, 1971-1972 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Danforth Foundation [Fellowship grant], 1971-1972 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Davies, Don, 1971-1972 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Doyle, John, 1973-1974 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Fetter, Robert, 1971-1972 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - Gores, Harold, 1971-1972 (Box 6, Folder 20)
    - Hatanaka, Francis, 1973-1975 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - Hiscock, Ira, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Hoerlein, Paul, 1973-1980 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - Howe, Harold, 1968-1972 (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - James, Thomas, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 25)
    - Johnson, Sidney, 1972-1975 (Box 6, Folder 26)
    - Jones, Ernest, 1972-1975 (Box 6, Folder 27)
    - Jones, Johnnie, 1973-1975 (Box 6, Folder 28)
    - Kalp, Karl, 1972-1973, 1978, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 29)
    - Kudlaty, Frank, 1974-1975 (Box 6, Folder 30)
    - Lancaster, Oliver, 1972-1983 (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - Lataille, Ralph, 1973-1979 (Box 6, Folder 32)
    - McCutcheon, Aubrey, 1971-1972 (Box 7, Folder 33)
    - Morison, Elting E., 1970-1971 (Box 7, Folder 34)
    - Nyquist, Ewald B., 1970-1971 (Box 7, Folder 35)
    - Oda, Margaret, 1972-1973, 1977 (Box 7, Folder 36)
    - O'Donnell, Lorena, 1972-1973 (Box 7, Folder 37)
    - Oliver, Raymond, 1973-1975 (Box 7, Folder 38)
    - Parpart, Edmund R., 1973-1974 (Box 7, Folder 39)
    - Pierce, Wendell H., 1970 (Box 7, Folder 40)
    - Reiss, A. J., Jr., 1970-1971 (Box 7, Folder 41)
    - Rigby, Avard A., 1972 (Box 7, Folder 42)
    - Rodriguez, Victor, 1973-1974 (Box 7, Folder 43)
    - Sandro, Patrick, 1973-1974 (Box 7, Folder 44)
    - Sloane, Robert, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 45)
    - Smith, Rodney, 1973-1981 (Box 7, Folder 46)
    - Stehly, Catherine, 1973-1985 (Box 7, Folder 47)
    - Stimbert, E. C., 1971 (Box 7, Folder 48)
    - Thomas, Arthur C., 1972 (Box 7, Folder 49)
    - Thornton, Cecil, 1973-1974 (Box 7, Folder 50)
    - Wallace, DeWitt, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 51)
    - School superintendents, list of, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 52)
  - Subject files
    - General background information [criteria for submission of funding proposals], 1968-1969 (Box 8, Folder 53)
    - Charles Stewart Mott Foundation, 1969-1971 (Box 8, Folder 54)
    - United States. Office of Education
      - Drafts of MCP proposal, 1966-1970 (Box 8, Folder 55 - 60)
      - Proposal, 1970-1971 (Box 8, Folder 61 - 62)
      - Visit of Fellows to Washington, D.C., 1969-1973 (Box 8, Folder 63)
    - W. K. Kellogg Foundation
      - Basis for proposal, 1950 (Box 8, Folder 64)
      - Revisions/updates of program, 1967-1970 (Box 8, Folder 65 - 68)
      - Revisions/updates of program, 1970-1973 (Box 9, Folder 69 - 71)
      - Termination of program, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 72)
      - Annual report, 1973-1974 (Box 9, Folder 73)
      - Final report, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 74)
  - Semester files
    - 1969 [publicity, press releases announcing MCP] (Box 9, Folder 75)
    - 1970-1971
      - General information (Box 9, Folder 76)
      - Budget/miscellaneous expenses [includes budget projections through 1980] (Box 9, Folder 77)
      - Colloquium (Box 9, Folder 78)
      - Evaluation committee (Box 9, Folder 79)
      - Evaluations [by Fellows after a year's elapsed time] (Box 9, Folder 80)
      - Faculty/resource persons (Box 9, Folder 81)
      - Form letters (Box 9, Folder 82)
      - Funding requests (Box 9, Folder 83)
      - Lecture series (Box 9, Folder 84 - 85)
      - Program description (Box 9, Folder 86)
      - Trips
        - Detroit, MI (Box 9, Folder 87)
        - Cambridge, MA (Box 9, Folder 88)
        - Washington, D.C. (Box 9, Folder 89)
    - 1971-1972
      - General information (Box 9, Folder 90 - 91)
      - Acceptances (Box 9, Folder 92)
      - Annual report (Box 10, Folder 93 - 94)
      - Budget/miscellaneous expenses [includes projections through 1980] (Box 10, Folder 95)
      - Colloquium (Box 10, Folder 96)
      - Evaluation committee (Box 10, Folder 97)
      - Evaluations by Fellows (Box 10, Folder 98)
      - Evaluations [by Fellows after a year's elapsed time] (Box 10, Folder 99)
      - Evaluations [criteria, summary of responses] (Box 10, Folder 100)
      - Funding requests (Box 10, Folder 101)
      - Lectures (Box 10, Folder 102)
      - Miller, John Perry [director of ISS, meeting with] (Box 10, Folder 103)
      - Planning (Box 10, Folder 104)
      - Resource persons (Box 10, Folder 105)
      - Seminars (Box 10, Folder 106 - 107)
      - Special events (Box 10, Folder 108)
      - Trips
        - New York, NY (Box 11, Folder 109)
        - Providence, RI (Box 11, Folder 110)
        - Trenton, NJ (Box 11, Folder 111)
        - Washington, D.C. (Box 11, Folder 112)
    - 1972-1973
      - General information (Box 11, Folder 113)
      - Annual report (Box 11, Folder 114)
      - Applicants (Box 11, Folder 115 - 116)
      - Colloquium (Box 11, Folder 117)
      - Evaluation committee (Box 11, Folder 118)
      - Faculty (Box 11, Folder 119)
      - I.S.P.S. 432 [Problems of Public Education and Law] (Box 11, Folder 120 - 121)
      - I.S.P.S. 482 [Case Studies in Educational Change] (Box 11, Folder 122)
      - I.S.P.S. 497 [Individual Reading and Research on Urban Administrative Problems] (Box 11, Folder 123 - 124)
      - Lectures (Box 11, Folder 125)
      - Planning (Box 11, Folder 126)
      - Proposal materials (Box 11, Folder 127)
      - Special events (Box 11, Folder 128)
    - 1973-1974
      - General information (Box 11, Folder 129)
      - Applicants (Box 11, Folder 130)
      - Funding proposal revision (Box 11, Folder 131)
      - Seminar topics (Box 11, Folder 132)
    - 1974-1975 [concluding year report] (Box 11, Folder 133)
- University of Connecticut Files, 1966-1970, Series III
  The series contains files compiled by Brownell during his time spent at the University of Connecticut, part of his joint appointment with Yale University, as a visiting lecturer and resource person in the area of advanced school administration in urban areas. The files are arranged alphabetically by topic and contain correspondence, memoranda, reports, and printed matter.
  - Appointment [joint appointment with Yale/University of Connecticut], 1966-1970 (Box 12, Folder 1 - 2)
  - Institute of Urban Research [advisory committee], 1967-1969 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - School of Education
    - Connecticut Precollegiate Enrichment Program (CONNPEP), 1967-1969 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Department of Education Administration, 1968-1970 (Box 12, Folder 5 - 7)
    - Education 410 [Evaluation and Research], 1967-1970 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Educational institutes [proposal aimed at area school districts], 1968 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Goals/objectives, 1966 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Graduate Teacher Education Committee, 1967-1968 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Inner City Committee, 1968 (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Seminar for superintendents of schools in Connecticut, 1966-1967 (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Short courses committee [summer school], 1969-1970 (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - Yale-University of Connecticut Urban Extension Unit [proposal], 1967 (Box 12, Folder 15)